Guide to the Steve Fitch Photographs
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Steve Fitch photographs
1970-2017
WA Photos Folio 174
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
25
9 boxes
Photographs created by Steve Fitch that document sites chiefly in the American West, 1970-2016, and printed 1990-2017. The collection contains 83 prints from his photographic projects, which include views of the vernacular roadside of highways, such as neon motel signs and hand-painted business signs, drive-in movie theaters, abandoned buildings, and radio towers. Photographs include sites in Arizona, California, Colorado, Kansas, Michigan, Montana, Nebraska, Nevada, New Mexico, Oklahoma, South Dakota, Texas, Utah, and Wyoming.
Fitch, Steve, 1949-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Paul Kopeikin Gallery on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 2017.
Ten prints: gift of Steve Fitch, 2017. For more information see entries for items in this guide.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Black-and-white Photographs, 1970-2016. II. Color Photographs, 1990-2000. III. Color Inkjet Prints, 1980-2017. IV. Color Inkjet Prints Panoramas, 2013-2016.
Steve Fitch (born 1949)
Steve Fitch graduated from the University of California at Berkeley in 1971 with a Bachelor of Arts degree in anthropology. He then worked as an instructor and darkroom supervisor at the Berkeley Art Studio of the Associated Students of the University of California while simultaneously working on a project photographing the vernacular roadside of American highways. Photographs from this project, which benefitted from two fellowships from the National Endowment for the Arts in 1973 and 1975, appeared in his book, Diesels and Dinosaurs: Photographs from the American Highway (Berkeley, California: Long Run Press, 1976).
Fitch earned a Master of Arts in Photography from the University of New Mexico in Albuquerque in 1978. He was then a visiting assistant professor in the Department of Fine Arts at the University of Colorado, Boulder, from 1979 to 1985. He also collaborated with other photographers, including Linda Connor, Rick Dingus, John Pfahl, and Charles Roitz, in a project, Marks and Measures: Rock Art in Modern Art Context, funded by a fellowship from the National Endowment for the Arts in 1981. This project photographically documented prehistoric Native American pictograph and petroglyph sites in the American West and led to their co-authored book, Marks in Place: Contemporary Responses to Rock Art (Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press, 1988) with essays by Polly Schaafsma and Keith Davis as well as a foreword by Lucy Lippard.
From 1986 to 1990, Fitch was a lecturer in the Visual Arts Program at Princeton University. He then returned to New Mexico and began photographing the High Plains. In 1999, he received the Eliot Porter Fellowship from the New Mexico Council for Photography to complete the project. Photographs from this project appeared in his book, Gone: Photographs of Abandonment on the High Plains (Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press, 2003).
Since 1990, Fitch has taught photography at the Santa Fe University of Art and Design (formerly known as The College of Santa Fe).
In 2011, Fitch published Motel Signs (Portland, Oregon: Nazraeli Press, 2011). He also contributed photographs to Steve Bogener, William E. Tydeman, Barry Holstun Lopez, et al, Llano Estacado: An Island in the Sky (Lubbock: Texas Tech University Press, 2011). In 2016, he published American Motel Signs 1980-2008 (London: The Velvet Cell, 2016) and in 2018 he published Vanishing Vernacular: Western Landmarks (Staunton, Virginia: George F. Thompson Publishing, 2018).
Scope and Contents
Photographs created by Steve Fitch that document sites chiefly in the American West, 1970-2016, and printed 1990-2017. The collection contains 83 prints from his photographic projects, which include views of the vernacular roadside of highways, such as neon motel signs and hand-painted business signs, drive-in movie theaters, abandoned buildings, and radio towers. Photographs include sites in Arizona, California, Colorado, Kansas, Michigan, Montana, Nebraska, Nevada, New Mexico, Oklahoma, South Dakota, Texas, Utah, and Wyoming.
Signed, titled, and dated by the photographer on versos of prints.
Conditions Governing Access
The Steve Fitch Photographs are the physical property of the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University. Literary rights, including copyright, belong to the authors or their legal heirs and assigns. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Drive-in theaters -- West (U.S.) -- Pictorial works; Neon signs -- West (U.S.) -- Pictorial works; Painted signs and signboards -- West (U.S.) -- Pictorial works; Radio and television towers -- West (U.S.) -- Pictorial works; Roadside architecture -- West (U.S.) -- Pictorial works; Arizona -- Pictorial works; California -- Pictorial works; Colorado -- Pictorial works; Kansas -- Pictorial works; Michigan -- Pictorial works; Montana -- Pictorial works; Nebraska -- Pictorial works; Nevada -- Pictorial works; New Mexico -- Pictorial works; Oklahoma -- Pictorial works; South Dakota -- Pictorial works; Texas -- Pictorial works; Utah -- Pictorial works; West (U.S.) -- Pictorial works; Wyoming -- Pictorial works; Inkjet prints; Photographic prints; Photographs; Paul Kopeikin Gallery; Fitch, Steve, 1949-
- Black-and-white Photographs, 1970–2016
  Scope and Contents
  Views chiefly of the American West created 1970-1974 and printed in 2010-2016 as black-and-white gelatin silver prints 16 x 18.75 inches (40.7 x 47.7 centimeters) and 20 x 16 inches (50.8 x 40.7 centimeters).
  Arrangement
  Organized under eleven headings: Arizona, California, Colorado, Michigan, Nevada, New Mexico, Oklahoma, South Dakota, Texas, Utah, and Wyoming.
  - Arizona
    - Billboard, Highway 180, Grand Canyon, Arizona, printed in 2016; image created 1972; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 1)
    - Motel, Highway 80, Gila Bend, Arizona, printed in 2015; image created 1973; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 2)
    - Motel, Highway 66, Holbrook, Arizona, printed in 2015; image created 1973; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 3)
    - Tourist lady, Highway 66, Meteor Crater, Arizona, printed in 2016; image created 1971; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 4)
    - Truck stop sign, Highway 86, Benson, Arizona, printed in 2016; image created 1972; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 5)
  - California
    - Motel sign, Highway 101, Ukiah, California, printed in 2015; image created 1974; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 6)
    - Sign, Highway 101, Ukiah, California, printed in 2016; image created 1974; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 7)
    - Tri-City Drive-in Theater, Highway I-10, Loma Linda, California, printed in 2015; image created 1974; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 8)
    - Truck stop, Highway 58, Bakersfield, California, printed in 2015; image created 1972; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 9)
    - Van Nuys Drive-in Theater, Highway I-5, Van Nuys, California, printed in 2010; image created 1973; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 10)
    - Victory Drive-in Theater, San Fernando Valley, California, printed in 2010; image created 1973; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 11)
  - Colorado
    - Sign, Highway 40, Dinosaur, Colorado, printed in 2016; image created 1974; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 12)
  - Michigan
    - Diorama, Highway I-75, Gaylord, Michigan, printed in 2015; image created 1973; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 13)
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Gift of Steve Fitch, 2017
  - Nevada
    - Abandoned truck stop, Highway I-80, Winnemucca, Nevada, printed in 2016; image created 1970; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 14)
    - Elko, Nevada, 1974; 1 black-and-white print, 50.8 x 40.7 centimeters (Box 1 (Oversize), Folder 15)
  - New Mexico
    - Albuquerque, New Mexico, 1974; 1 black-and-white print, 50.8 x 40.7 centimeters (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 16)
    - Billboard, Highway 66, near Albuquerque, New Mexico, printed in 2016; image created 1972; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 17)
    - Motel, Highway 85, Truth or Consequences, New Mexico, printed in 2016; image created 1973; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 18)
    - Truck stop waitress, Highway 66, Gallup, New Mexico, printed in 2015; image created 1972; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 19)
  - Oklahoma
    - Motel, Highway 66, Elk City, Oklahoma, printed in 2016; image created 1973; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 20)
    - Snake pit operator, Highway 66, Sayre, Oklahoma, printed in 2016; image created 1972; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 21)
    - Snake pit operator, Highway 66, Sayre, Oklahoma, printed in 2015; image created 1973; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 22)
  - South Dakota
    - Motel, Highway 85, Deadwood, South Dakota, printed in 2015; image created 1972; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 23)
  - Texas
    - Chalk Hill Drive-in Theater, Highway 80, Dallas, Texas, printed in 2014; image created 1973; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 24)
    - Chalk Hill Drive-in Theater, Highway 80, Dallas, Texas, printed in 2015; image created 1973; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 25)
    - Circle Drive-in Theater, Highway 81, Waco, Texas, printed in 2015; image created 1973; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 26)
    - El Rancho Drive-in Theater, Dalhart, Texas, printed in 2015; image created 1973; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 27)
    - Trail Drive-in Theater, San Antonio, Texas, printed in 2010; image created 1973; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 28)
  - Utah
    - Dinosaur, Highway 40, Vernal, Utah, printed in 2015; image created 1974; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 29)
    - Gas station, Highway 40, Jensen, Utah, printed in 2015; image created 1971; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 30)
  - Wyoming
    - Motel signs, Highway 80, Cheyenne, Wyoming, printed in 2015; image created 1974; 1 black-and-white print, 40.7 x 47.7 centimeters (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 31)
- Color Photographs, 1990–2000
  Views chiefly of the American West created 1990-2000 and printed as color photographs on Fuji Crystal Archive paper 16 x 20 inches (40.7 x 50.8 centimeters) and 20 x 24 inches (50.8 x 61 centimeters).
  Organized under four headings: Colorado, Montana, New Mexico, and Wyoming.
  - Colorado
    - Bathroom in Motel, southeastern Colorado, 1994 February 11; 1 color print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 32)
    - Living room in a house in Aguilar, eastern Colorado, 1995 November 3; 1 color print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 33)
    - Living room in a house near Ludlow, eastern Colorado, 1999 July 6; 1 color print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 34)
  - Montana
    - Living room in a house in Carlyle, eastern Montana, 2000 June 8; 1 color print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 35)
  - New Mexico
    - Church with stars on the ceiling near Concepcion, eastern New Mexico, 1992 March 10; 1 color print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 36)
    - Dance hall in Yeso, eastern New Mexico, 1991 January 5; 1 color print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 37)
    - Exterior view of a house near Las Vegas, New Mexico, 1990 July 21; 1 color print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 38)
    - Gymnasium in a Work Projects Administration-built school in Wheatland, eastern New Mexico, 1992 July 17; 1 color print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 39)
    - Hallway view through a house in Ocate, eastern New Mexico, 1991 August 31; 1 color print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 40)
    - Honky-tonk near Vaughn, eastern New Mexico, 1991 May 21; 1 color print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 41)
      Image printed backwards
    - Honky-tonk near Vaughn, eastern New Mexico, 1991 May 21; 1 color print, 50.8 x 61 centimeters (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 42)
    - School floor in McAllister, eastern New Mexico, 1994 January 6; 1 color print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 43)
    - View inside a house in Ancho, eastern New Mexico, 2000 May 14; 1 color print, 50.8 x 61 centimeters (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 44)
  - Wyoming
    - Classroom in Keeline, eastern Wyoming, 1995 June 7; 1 color print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 3 (Oversize), Folder 45)
- Color Inkjet Prints, 1980–2017
  Views chiefly of the American West created 1980-2010 and printed in 2007-2017 as color inkjet prints 16 x 20 inches (40.7 x 50.8 centimeters) and 20 x 16 inches (50.8 x 40.7 centimeters).
  Organized under eight headings: Arizona, Colorado, Kansas, Montana, Nebraska, Nevada, New Mexico, and Texas.
  - Arizona
    - Greyhound Motel, Tucson, Arizona, printed in 2017; image created 1980 December 30; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 46)
    - La Mesita Lodge, Highway 60, Mesa, Arizona, printed in 2016; image created 1980 December 28; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 47)
    - Oasis Court, Benson, Arizona, printed in 2016; image created 1980 December 30; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 48)
    - Starlite Motel, Highway 60, Mesa, Arizona, printed in 2014; image created 1980 December 28; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 49)
  - Colorado
    - Along U.S. Highway 491 south of Cortez, Colorado, printed in 2017; image created 2007 July 21; 1 inkjet print, 50.8 x 40.7 centimeters (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 50)
    - U.S. Highway 40, Dinosaur, Colorado, printed in 2017; image created 1982 March 16; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 51)
    - Utah-Colorado state line, Highway 50, printed in 2017; image created 1982 October 16; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 52)
  - Kansas
    - U.S. Highway 36, Atwood, Kansas, printed in 2017; image created 1982 August; 1 inkjet print, 50.8 x 40.7 centimeters (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 53)
  - Montana
    - U.S. Highway 12, Harlowton, Montana, printed in 2015; image created 1998 June; 1 inkjet print, 50.8 x 40.7 centimeters (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 54)
  - Nebraska
    - AA Motel, Holdrege, Nebraska, printed in 2010; image created 1981 May 22; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 55)
    - Between Merriman and Hyannis, Nebraska, printed in 2017; image created 2001 May; 1 inkjet print, 50.8 x 40.7 centimeters (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 56)
  - Nevada
    - Abandoned truck stop, Winnemucca, Nevada, printed in 2017; image created 1984 June 19; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 57)
    - Las Vegas, Nevada, printed in 2016; image created 2002 August; 1 inkjet print, 50.8 x 40.7 centimeters (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 58)
  - New Mexico
    - Along I-40 near Milagro, New Mexico, printed in 2016; image created 2010 October 10; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 59)
    - Arrow Motel, Highway 84, Espanola, New Mexico, printed in 2016; image created 1982 March 23; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 60)
    - Bel Shore Motel, Highway 70, Deming, New Mexico, printed in 2016; image created 1980 December 31; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 61)
    - Between Trujillo and Las Vegas, New Mexico, printed in 2016; image created 2009 September 9; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 62)
    - Blue Swallow Motel, Highway 66, Tucumcari, New Mexico, printed in 2016; image created 1990 July; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 63)
    - Capri Motel, Highway 87, Raton, New Mexico, printed in 2016; image created 1980 December 18; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 64)
    - Fort Union Drive-in Theater, Las Vegas, New Mexico, printed in 2017; image created 1982 July 12; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 65)
    - Grand View Motel, Highway 66, Albuquerque, New Mexico, printed in 2015; image created 1980 July; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 66)
    - Grand View Motel, Highway 66, Albuquerque, New Mexico, printed in 2016; image created 1980 December 21; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 67)
    - Grand View Motel, Highway 87, Raton, New Mexico, printed in 2016; image created 1980 December 18; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 68)
    - Highway 66, Tucumcari, New Mexico, printed in 2007; image created 2006 September 9; 1 inkjet print, 50.8 x 40.7 centimeters (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 69)
    - It'll Do Motel, Highway 66, Grants, New Mexico, printed in 2015; image created 1982 January 11; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 70)
    - Jaguar with a rattlesnake, tail petroglyph, Three Rivers, New Mexico, printed in 2017; image created 1983 January 10; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 71)
    - Texan Motel, Highway 64, Raton, New Mexico, printed in 2016; image created 1980 December 19; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 72)
    - Villa Motel, Highway 66, Albuquerque, New Mexico, printed in 2016; image created 1980 December 21; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 73)
  - Texas
    - Highway 67, north of Presidio, Texas, printed in 2017; image created 2006 March 2; 1 inkjet print, 50.8 x 40.7 centimeters (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 74)
    - Motel, Highway 287, Hedley, Texas, printed in 2015; image created 1981 January 8; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 75)
    - Radio tower near Tulia, Texas, printed in 2016; image created 2009 March 15; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 76)
    - Radio tower near Umbarger, Texas, printed in 2016; image created 2005 March 11; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 77)
    - Radio tower west of Levelland, Texas, printed in 2016; image created 2004 June 6; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 78)
    - Western Hills Motel, Highway 90, Sanderson, Texas, printed in 2016; image created 1985 December 1; 1 inkjet print, 40.7 x 50.8 centimeters (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 79)
- Color Inkjet Prints Panoramas, 2013–2016
  Views of the American West created 2013-2016 as color inkjet prints 13 x 51.75 inches (33.1 x 131.5 centimeters) and smaller.
  Organized under three headings: Colorado, New Mexico, and Texas.
  - Colorado
    - Limon, Colorado, 2015 June 10; 1 inkjet print, 30.6 x 81 centimeters (Box 6 (Oversize))
  - New Mexico
    - Fort Sumner, New Mexico, 2013 March 13; 1 inkjet print, 30.9 x 130.9 centimeters (Box 7 (Oversize))
    - San Jon, New Mexico, 2016 March 6; 1 inkjet print, 30.6 x 113.7 centimeters (Box 8 (Oversize))
  - Texas
    - McCamey, Texas, 2014 August 23; 1 inkjet print, 33.1 x 131.5 centimeters (Box 9 (Oversize))